## **Axel Herve Patrick Masquelin**

Pre Doctoral Fellow – Bioengineering

**Address: Phone:** (317) 797-7965

University of Vermont Email: <a href="mailto:axel.masquelin@med.uvm.edu">axel.masquelin@med.uvm.edu</a>

Health Science Research Facility

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/axel-masquelin

Burlington, VT 05405 GitHub: https://github.com/axemasquelin

### **Summary:**

I am a trained biomedical engineer focused on the utilization of machine learning and mathematical modeling to improve diagnostic outcomes for patients. My current work primarily explores the use of deep learning for early lung cancer detection. Specifically, we are utilizing wavelet decompositions to reduce the number of examples needed for a deep learning algorithm to learn. Other fields of research included differentiation between Tuberculosis and lung cancer nodule from CT and X-ray images, and the application of pharmacokinetics to model drug dispersion/absorption within pulmonary nodules. My work has allowed me to collaborate extensively with numerous other investigators within the Cellular, Molecular, and Biomedical Sciences (CMB), Complex System Center, and the College of Engineering and Mathematical Sciences (CEMS).

## **Education:**

2018-08 - Present	University of Vermont, Burlington, VT, PhD in Bioengineering Department of Electrical & Biomedical Engineering
2013-08 - 2017-05	Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, B.S in Engineering College of Engineering - Biomedical Engineering

### **Professional Appointments:**

= = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = =	
2021 – Present	NIH F31 Pre-Doctoral Fellow, University of Vermont.
2019 - 2021	T-32 Pre-Doctoral Fellow, University of Vermont.
2018 - Present	Graduate Research Assistant, University of Vermont.
2017 - 2018	Discovery automation Engineer, Eli Lilly & Company.
2016 - 2018	Hardware Engineer, OmniVis LLC.
2016 - Present	Co-founder/Data Scientist, Predictive Wear Inc.
2016 - 2017	Operator / Undergrad Research, Purdue Rare Isotope Measurement Laboratory.

## **Books, Patents, Publications:**

### **Abstracts:**

- 2022 Masquelin A., Cheney N., Bates J.H.T., Kinsey C.M., "Looking at the Negative Using False Positives to Learn How Deep Neural Nets Classify Lung Cancer CT Images" *American Thoracic Society* 2021 *International Conference*, 2022.
- Masquelin A., Cheney N., Bates J.H.T., Kinsey C.M., "Refocusing Network Attention on Perinodular Features Improves Lung Cancer Classification" *Biomedical Engineering Society Conference*, 2021.
- 2021 Masquelin A., Cheney N., Bates J.H.T., Kinsey C.M., "Learning the Surrounding Parenchymal Features Improve Lung Cancer Classification," *American Thoracic Society 2021 International Conference*, 2021.
- 2020 Masquelin A., Cheney N., Bates J.H.T., Kinsey C.M., "Wavelet Decomposition Improving Deep Learning Prediction Aided by Pre-existing Knowledge," *Biomedical Engineering Society Conference*, 2020.

#### **Axel Masquelin**

- 2020 Masquelin A., Whitney D., Stevenson C., Spira A., Bates J.H., San Jose Estepar R., Kinsey C. "Radiomics in Deep Learning Feature Augmentation for Lung Cancer Prediction," *American Thoracic Society 2020 International Conference*. [Online]. Available: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2020.201.1\_MeetingAbstracts.A7690">https://doi.org/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2020.201.1\_MeetingAbstracts.A7690</a>
- 2020 Casey D., Masquelin A.H., Bou Jawde S.A., Hermann J., Suki B., Bates J.H.T., "Gene Expression Modules in Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis and Nonspecific Interstitial Pneumonia: A Meta-Analysis," *American Thoracic Society* 2020 International Conference. [Online]. Available: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2020.201.1">https://doi.org/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2020.201.1</a> MeetingAbstracts.A4027
- Erdreich B., McClure K., Masquelin A.H., McGinnis R., Wshah S., Bates J.H. "Using Wearable Sensors and Deep learning to Categorize and Detect Different Patterns of Breathing in Healthy Subjects" *American Thoracic Society* 2020 International Conference. [Online]. Available: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2020.201.1">https://doi.org/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2020.201.1</a> MeetingAbstracts.A6164
- Masquelin A., Bates J.H.T., Kinsey C.M., "Wavelet Decomposition for Differentiating Benign vs Malignant Lung Nodules," American Thoracic Society 2019 International Conference. [Online]. Available: https://www.atsjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1164/ajrccm-conference.2019.199.1 MeetingAbstracts.A5483
- 2019 Masquelin A., Alshaabi T., Connolly, S., Elhajj, A., Estepar, R.S.J., Bates, J.H.T., Kinsey, C.M., "Learning Radiomics Diagnostic Important from Machine Learning Algorithms," Biomedical Engineering Society Conference, 2019.

#### **Patents:**

2019 Albaugh, M.D., Argote, P., Masquelin, A., Hoilett, O., Drakopoulos, M., "Impedance Based Compression Legging System," U.S. Provisional Pat. Ser. No. 62/856,410, filed [March 5th, 2019].

#### **Publications:**

- A. H. Masquelin, N. Cheney, C. M. Kinsey, and J. H. T. Bates, "Wavelet decomposition facilitates training on small datasets for medical image classification by deep learning," *Histochem Cell Biol*, Jan. 2021, doi: 10.1007/s00418-020-01961-y.
- **2020** K. McClure, B. Erdreich, J. H. T. Bates, R. S. McGinnis, A. Masquelin, and S. Wshah, "Classification and Detection of Breathing Patterns with Wearable Sensors and Deep Learning," *Sensors (Basel)*, vol. 20, no. 22, Nov. 2020, doi: 10.3390/s20226481.

## **Invited Speaker:**

- 2021 University of Vermont Lung Center Seminar, "Learning the Surrounding Parenchymal Features Improve Lung Cancer Classification", June. 22<sup>nd</sup>, 2021.
- 2021 University of Vermont Lung Center Seminar, "Wavelet Decomposition Facilitates Training on Small Datasets for Medical Image Classification by Deep Learning", Jan. 19<sup>th</sup>, 2021.
- **2020** American Thoracic Society 2020 International Conference. "Radiomics in Deep Learning Feature Augmentation for Lung Cancer Prediction", Dec 2nd.
- **2020** Electrical and Bioengineering Seminar, University of Vermont, "Learning Radiomic Feature Importance for Deep Learning Application", Jan. 24<sup>th</sup>, 2020.
- **2020** University of Vermont Lung Center Seminar, "Learning Radiomic Feature Importance for Deep Learning Application", Jan. 7<sup>th</sup>, 2020.
- **2019** Biomedical Engineering Society 2019 Conference "Learning Radiomics Diagnostic Important from Machine Learning Algorithms," Oct. 16-19<sup>th</sup>.
- 2019 University of Vermont's Translational Global Infectious Diseases Research Center (TGIR), "Webbing Radiomics and Deep Neural Networks: A Malignancy Story". Oct. 31.

#### **Axel Masquelin**

2019 University of Vermont Lung Center Seminar, "Riding the Wavelet – Staying Superficial in Deep Learning", Apr. 16<sup>th</sup>, 2019.

### **Awards and Honors**

2021	NIH Ruth L. Kirschstein Predoctoral Individual National Research Service Award, F31 Predoctoral Fellowship
2021	Abstract Scholarship, American Thoracic Society Conference 2021
2020	Abstract Scholarship, American Thoracic Society Conference 2020
2019	Pre-Doctoral Fellowship, Vermont Lung Center T-32
2017	Rice Business Plan Finalist: PathVis
2017	Second place at Purdue's Burton D. Morgan Business Plan Competition

## **Outreach and Mentoring**

#### **Outreach:**

2021 Invited speaker for the UVM Career Center, Topic: STEM Jumpstart: Personal Statement for Graduate

Schools.

2021 Invited speaker for South Burlington High "Exploring the Human Machine" science elective, topic:

Respiratory system.

#### Leadership:

2019 - present Elected Member of the Larner College of Medicine Graduate Student Council. Act as liaison between the

Postdoctoral Association and Graduate Student Council. Assisted in the organization and advertising of the

Postdoctoral Fellowship Workshop in the Larner College of Medicine.

#### **Mentoring:**

2021 Master Student Mentoring: Alyx Cleveland. Mentoring Alyx Cleveland on the application of deep learning

methodologies for medical datasets. Assisting in comprehending electrical impedance tomography

principles, chest geometry, and potential correlation between disease state and impedance signals.

2019 - 2020 High School mentor for Young Scientist: William Suratt. Supervised and mentored William Suratt on the

application of deep learning methodologies within the field of bioengineering and pulmonary medicine. Developed example codes, small demo lectures, and provided feedback on project direction for parameter

estimation of nitrogen washout models.

# **Advisory Boards & Peer Reviewer**

Peer reviewer for the following journals:

- Fluctuation and Noise Letters

Member of Biomedical Engineering Society and the American Thoracic Association.